Guide to the Victor P. Saladini papers, 1952-1989
Department of Special Collections
Salandini, Victor, P.,
1952-1989
M0686
Victor P. Saladini
9.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Roman Catholic priest who was both a scholar of farm labor problems in California and an active participant with the Mexican American labor movement, particularly the United Farm Workers.
Administrative Information
Access
None.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Father Salandini, 1993.
Provenance
Gift of Father Salandini, 1993.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Includes correspondence, research files, talks, papers, publications, parish work, community work, articles and information on Cesar Chavez (and correspondence with), book reviews, farm labor contracts, and research on the Reclamation Law of 1902. Related materials: Victor P. Salandini papers, 1949-1992 (M249)
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Allen, Steve.; Alinsky, Saul David, 1909-1972.; Anderson, James.; Chacon, Pete.; Chavez, Cesar, 1927-; Châavez, Fernando.; Galarza, Ernesto, 1905-; Itliong, Larry, 1913 or 14-; Jenkins, Craig.; Metzler, William H., 1897-; Taylor, Paul.; Yellen, Ben, 1907-; Catholic Church--California.; National Brown Beret Organization.; United Farm Workers of America.; Agricultural laborers--California.; Labor disputes--California.; Mexican Americans--Civil rights.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, l950-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence with Fr. James Anderson from Puerto Rico, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Lobbying work for Cesar Chavez, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence to Fernando Chavez, son of Cesar Chavez, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Letters Notre Dame University 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence with Cesar Chavez (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Lobbying Washington, D. C. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Interview with Time Magazine, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Notes and letters of talks in Canada, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Short-Handled Hoe research, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Research on Associated for Cesar Chavez in ca. 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Research on Saul Alinsky, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Research for INS, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Information on Farm Workers in "Christopher News Notes," 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Interview with Larry Itliong of UFWOC, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Workers Conference and notes on Delano stay, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Farm Labor Research, 19741974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- ALRA Research, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- San Diego County UFW, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Proof that Fr. Salandini did research for UFW1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Proof that Fr. Salandini did research for UFW1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Information on Nonviolence UFW (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Strike in Hollister and Fr. Salandini's role,1981 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Priests Meetings about Coachella Strike1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Variety of Items on UFW (Box 4, Folder 14)
- March to Sacramento, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Proposition 22, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Variety of Information on UFW, early years (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Correspondence with K. Cramer - help with her book, "Mighty Hard Road," 1969 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Research on Mechanization (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Research on Mechanization (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Interviews with farm workers and tape of Chavez, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Articles on Bracero Program (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Research on Guimarra, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Hunsinger Report, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Grape Strike - early years (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Pesticides (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Santa Maria, California and Research, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Notes on Dr. Ernesto Galarza (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Coachella Strike, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Notes on workshop with Chavez, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Interviews, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Fact sheet on early years of Grape Strike (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Research for vice-president of UFW (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Research notes on doctoral dissertation (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Dedication of Delano Medical Clinic, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Nadar study on "Power and Land in California" 1971 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Chiquita Banana Boycott, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Second Constitutional Convention, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Fact sheet in Spanish, Lettuce strike of 1975, and announcement of 1st anniversary of strike (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Thank you letter in Spanish from farm worker for dental work, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Research on raisins and a proposed study done by Salandini (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Lectures to High Schools (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Prof. Salandini: Publications Coordinator at SDSU (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Paper, "The Operation of Labor Union Contracts in California Agriculture," 1972 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Rural sociological study - Paper delivered at San Francisco, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Paper delivered at Denver, Colorado 1978 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Paper, "UFW in California: A Brief History," 1978 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Paper delivered at Pomona, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- "Catholic Rural Life" - Publication, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Paper: "Gains of Farm Workers in California due to the UFW, " 1978 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Paper: "Views of the Farm Worker on Mechanization, "1973 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Talk in Las Vegas on Tomato Strike, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- "Journal of Mexican American History" Publications of Fr. Salandini, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Academic work of Fr. Salandini at SDSU (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Invocation at Washington, D. C. 1966 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Agricultural College talks at UCDavis, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Programs of talks given by Fr. Salandini at SW Labor Conferences (Box 6, Folder 2)
- "El Chicano" Publications 1974 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- San Diego County Border Task Force, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Two Graduation Talks - 1952, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Letter published in "Commonweal," 1966 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Profile of Cesar Chavez in "Long Island Catholic," 1966 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Paper: "Illegal Mexican Aliens in Borderlands Society," 1978 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Invocation at Washington, D. C. - 1966 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Young Christian Workers, 1950-l969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Help to a family in Anthoy, California 1956 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Help to a farm worker in San Diego, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Memorabilia, El Centro Parish 1962 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Correspondence with Prof. Rochin from UCDavis, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Correspondence with Craig Jenkins,. 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Newman Center at UCDavis, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Brown Berets and Fr. Salandini (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Manpower Conference at Washington, D. C. -1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Copies of sermons in 1960's (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Community Relations Board at San Diego, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Talk to Bureau of Labor Statistics at Washington, D. C. - 1969 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Parts of Dissertation published in US Senate Committee Hearings1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- National Catholic Review on Salandini's book (Box 7, Folder 14)
- "San Diego-Tijuana Borderlands," Talk at Mesa College1992 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- List of books mentioning Fr. Salandini's work (Box 7, Folder 16)
- A bibliography published by Wayne State and a list of Salandini's publications, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Paper, "Greater Awareness of Farm Labor," 1981 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Sociological Abstracts, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Talk given for Western Social Science Association in Denver, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Paper for Rural Sociological Society in San Francisco, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Paper on Catholic Social Teachings in San Francisco, l980 (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Paper delivered in San Diego, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Condensed version of dissertation in the Journal of Behavioural Economics1973 (Box 7, Folder 24)
- 1 California Farm Labor Problems, Part I 1961 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- "Farm Labor Developments" (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Key articles on Mechanization (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Material used in dissertation (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Research on Lettuce Harvestor for UFW (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Interviews with farm workers in Calexico "Union Meeting," 1972 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Dissertation Material (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Dissertation Material (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Interviews with farm workers in Coachella, California 1974 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Interviews in Coachella, California 1975 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Interviews with UFW and Teamsters in Coachella, California (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Interviews with UFW and Teamsters in Coachella, California 1977 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Mechanization research for Doctoral dissertation (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Labor unionism in agriculture (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Copies of checks and articles on Public Law 1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Copy of dissertation read by Carey McWilliams (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Research on California Farm Bureau (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Kern County Research 1960's (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Research on California Farm Bureau (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Ralph Nadar Pesticide Study 1972 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Research on Mechanization for UFW at UCDavis,1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Mechanization research for UFW at UCDavis,1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Proof that Salandini's dissertation is in Library of Congress 1970 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Interview with Secretary of Labor Wirtz and Congressmen (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Information used in Doctoral dissertation (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Raisin research in Fresno for UFW - 1971 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Research on Illegals 1976 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Attacks on Cesar Chavez (Box 10, Folder 7)
- UFW Union Label (Box 10, Folder 8)
- National Farm Worker Ministry (Box 10, Folder 9)
- "Fresno Bee," Farm labor articles - 1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- "Christian Science Monitor," on Chavez - 1971 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Magazine articles on Chavez, 1966-1971 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Variety of articles on Chavez (esp. Cover story in Time), July 4 1969 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- "Farm Labor Journal" interview with Cesar Chavez - May 1972 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Magazine articles on Chavez, 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- "The Catholic Worker" interview with Cesar Chavez1971 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Description. of UFW headquarter in La Paz by the Los Angeles Times - Oct 11 1973 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Lettuce Boycott (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Excerpts of Chavez tape in Santa Maria - 1971 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Cesar Chavez and the Church - 1968 (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Red-baiting of Chavez (Box 11, Folder 1)
- General principles of farm labor contracts (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Articles on UFW - early 1960's (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Schenley contract of 1970 and Maggio contract1970 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Green Card Labor and the Delano Grape Strike1968 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Guild Boycott of 1972-1973 and Gallo Boycott of 1975 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Meeting of Salandini with Chavez in Montreal,Canada - Oct 18 1969 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Variety of articles on Chavez, 1960-l979 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Letter from Chavez to Senator H. Williams -1966 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Profile of Chavez 1969 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Variety of articles on- Chavez - 1980's (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Guidelines on how to organize a boycott (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Course outlines of Salandini's classes at San Diego State 1974-1978 (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Field work for class credit for Salandini's students, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Excerpts from Senate hearings on Farm labor organization in 1930-1949ca. 1930-1949 (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Study by Paul Taylor on Mexican Labor - 1930 (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Variety of material used in Doctoral dissertation (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Material by Salandini while in Montreal,Canada 1969 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Famous cartoon of Cesar Chavez - 1968 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Newsletter on Chicano studies - 1975 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Borderlands study - 1976 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Impact of Mexico's peso devaluation on U.S. border cities - 1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Indian farm workers of Winnepeg, Manitoba in Canada - 1976 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Correspondence on Farm Labor Research (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Socioeconomic Impact of the Mexican Illegal Alien on San Diego County (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Chapter on Farm Labor in California (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Papers on farm laborers (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Impact of Illegal Aliens on the county of San Diego (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Correspondence on professional endeavors at SDSU (Box 13, Folder 1)
- INS annual report - 1972 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- INS annual report - 1973 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- INS annual report - 1974 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Report of Select Commission on western hemisphere immigration - 1968 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- INS annual report - 1975 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- 1975 Lesko Report 1975 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Salandirli farm labor research at UCDavis,1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- UCDavis unpublished study on Farm Labor obtained by Salandini (Box 13, Folder 0)
- Biographical sketch of Fr. Salandini (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Studies by Dr. William Metzler, advisor to Salandini, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Metzler's studies on farm workers and farm mechanization -1961 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Metzler's studies on migrant farm workers (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Metzler's studies on farm production and mechanization (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Metzler's studies on migrant farm workers (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Metzler's studies on farm workers - (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Metzler's studies on labor (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Metzler's studies on farm workers (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Correspondence with Dr. Metzler on Doctoral dissertation, 1968-1969 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Articles and correspondence with Dr. Ben Yellen 1968 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen 1969 (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Dr. Yellen notes,1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen, 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Dr. Yellen's correspondence 1972 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Articles on Dr. Yellen, Apr 1972-May 1972 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen 1972 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Dr. Yellen's newsletters 1972 (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Dr. Yellen newsletter June 1973 (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen, 1976-1977 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Correspondence with Dr..Yellen 1976, 1978-1979 (Box 15, Folder 11)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen, 1984-1985 (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Dr. Moore's paper on the Reclamation Act and Williamson Act 1972 (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Dr. Taylor's articles on land and water reform (Box 15, Folder 14)
- Articles on water and land reform (Box 15, Folder 15)
- Articles on the Anti-Monopoly 160-Acre Water Law (Box 15, Folder 16)
- Imperial Valley articles on the Reclamation Law (Box 15, Folder 17)
- Articles and information on the Reclamation Law (Box 15, Folder 18)
- Paul Taylor's testimony on migrant labor Jan 1972 (Box 15, Folder 19)
- "The Washington Monthly" - 1971 article on Dr. Yellen 1971 (Box 15, Folder 20)
- "Fresno Bee" - Water problem articles from Feb 1973-July 1973 (Box 15, Folder 21)
- Fresno State University student work on Reclamation Law (Box 15, Folder 22)
- Congressional record on Reclamation Law (Box 15, Folder 23)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen 1973 (Box 15, Folder 24)
- Information on Dr. Yellen and Reclamation Act (Box 15, Folder 25)
- Key articles on land reform (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Articles in the Los Angeles Times and by Ruben Salazar 1968 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Dr. Yellen papers (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Dr. Yellen correspondence (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Dr. Yellen newsletters (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Dr. Yellen newsletters (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Dr. Yellen correspondence (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Study of farm labor in Manitoba, Canada 1970's (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Lettuce Boycott of 1970; Fact sheets on various grocery stores1970 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Letters from Cesar Chavez and Pete Chacon regarding farm labor 1972 (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Information from Constitutional Convention 1973 (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Articles used by Fr. Salandini in farm labor classes at SDSU (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Photos of Fr. Salandini with Indian leaders in Manitoba, Canada - 1976 (Box 16, Folder 13)
- 1970 pilgrimage to Washington, D. C.1970 (Box 16, Folder 14)
- Article used in Salandini's farm labor classes at SDSU (Box 16, Folder 15)
- SDSU publicity1976 (Box 16, Folder 16)
- Publicity on Salandini in "Catholic Star Herald"1976 (Box 16, Folder 17)
- Salandini and Chavez jailing 1966 (Box 16, Folder 18)
- Information on film nationally distributed in which Salandini appears (Box 16, Folder 19)
- March in Washington, D.C. (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Tortilla Priest Publicity 1971 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Publicity on New York Boycott 1970 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Publicity on Salandini in El Centro, 1957-1962 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Publicity on Salandini being fired from Fresno State College 1971 (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Publicity on Salandini in San Diego High Schools 1984 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Salandini publicity, 1991-1993 (Box 17, Folder 7)
- "National Catholic Reporter" References toSalandini 1984 (Box 17, Folder 8)
- 25th anniversary of his Ordination and a letter from Chavez 1977 (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Articles by Tortilla Priest in San Diego Review (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Article, "Travail of a Tortilla Priest" 1971 (Box 17, Folder 11)
- Teamsters General Contract (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Almaden Contract with UFW 1974 (Box 17, Folder 13)
- DiGiorgio Contractwith UFW 1967 (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Schenley Contract 1966, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 15)
- Gallo Contract 1976 (Box 17, Folder 16)
- Guimarra Contract with UFW (Box 17, Folder 17)
- Maggio Tostado, Inc. Contract in Spanish and English 1977 (Box 17, Folder 18)
- Wonder Palms Ranch Contract 1970 (Box 17, Folder 19)
- Inter-Harvest Contract 1976 (Box 17, Folder 20)
- "Brawley News" -photo with Fr. Salandini working with Dr. Yellen, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 21)
- Imperial Valley research (Box 17, Folder 22)
- Imperial Valley vs Imperial Irrigation District 1977 (Box 17, Folder 23)
- Congressional Record on Central Valley Project 1959 (Box 17, Folder 24)
- Imperial Valley Irrigation District (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Dr. Yellen newsletters, 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen, 1979-1980 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Various Dr. Yellen newsletters (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Variety of articles on Imperial Valley (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Excerpts of book on Colorado River; Ch. 7 on Imperial Valley (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Articles by Dr. Taylor, an eminent authority on the Reclamation Law (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Articles used by Salandini's students at SDSU to research the Reclamation Law (Box 18, Folder 9)
- Handbook of "How to do Research" - used by Salandini 's students (Box 18, Folder 10)
- Correspondence with Dr. Yellen - 1977 (Box 18, Folder 11)
- Paper, "Imperial Valley: Who has the Right tothe Land?" (Box 18, Folder 12)
- Paper, "Water, Land and Environment, Imperial Valley (Box 18, Folder 13)
- Paper, "Reclamation Law: the Imperial Valley Case" (Box 18, Folder 14)
- Paper, "The Reclamation Law of 1902: Acreage Limitation and (Box 18, Folder 15)
- The Reclamation Act (Box 18, Folder 16)
- Correspondence about money for Braceros (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Thesis, "Harvest Labor Problem in Imperial Valley" (Box 19, Folder 0)